Guide to the Lillian Russell Scrapbook, 1899-1951 CTC.1965.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Lillian Russell Scrapbook
1899-1951
CTC.1965.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
0.5 linear feet (1 mss. box)
This scrapbook details the career of the actress and singer Lillian Russell. Russell was one of the most popular performers of her era and became politically active during her later years. The scrapbook is composed mostly of newspaper clippings, but also includes correspondence, photographs, and other ephemera.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Margaret Mckee Crothers in March 1965.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Scope and Content Notes
The scrapbook primarily contains clipped newspaper and magazine articles in approximately chronological order. In most instances, the clippings are adhered to the scrapbook pages, but some clippings and articles are loose. This scrapbook has been disbound and its contents broken up into folders based on subject. It is assumed that the pages are still in their original order.
Note that some of the clippings are very fragile. Preservation photocopies of these items have been made and are available in the same folder as the originals. In some cases, preservation photocopies have replaced the original scrapbook pages. Researchers are encouraged to use these facsimiles.
The majority of the scrapbook contains materials related to Russell's career post 1904. There are a number of pages dedicated to her 1912 marriage to Alexander Pollock Moore, owner of the Pittsburgh Leader.
Biography
Lillian Russell was an American actress and singer and one of the more popular entertainers of her era. She became well-known in the 1880s performing light opera and musical comedies. She was a part of the Tony Pastor company, the Weber and Fields company, and eventually had her own Lillian Russell Opera Company.
In 1912, Russell married Alexander Pollock Moore, owner of the Pittsburgh Leader, and settled in Pittsburgh. During this time, she performed only sporadically. During her later years, Russell wrote a newspaper column on various topics including health, love, and beauty, became an advocate for women's suffrage, and participated in Marnie Corps recruiting efforts for World War I. In 1922, Russell traveled to Europe on an immigration fact-finding mission for President Harding. Following a short illness after her return, Lillian Russel passed away at her home in Pittsburgh.
This scrapbook was donated by Margaret Mckee Crothers in March 1965. Mrs. Crothers or her brother are presumed to be the creators of the scrapbook.
Cosmopolitan (1886).; Moore, Alexander P.; Pittsburgh leader (Pittsburgh, Pa.: Daily).; Russell, Lillian, 1861-1922; Actresses -- United States; Vaudeville -- United States
- Cover (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Frontispiece (Folder 2)
- Early days and comic opera (Folder 3)
- Strang, Lewis Clinton. 1900. Famous prima donnas. Boston: L. C. Page & company - Chapter III on Lillian Russell with annotations (Folder 4)
- Weber & Fields - Vanity Fair articles, 1899 (Folder 5)
- Red Book series of photographic portraits of Lillian Russell, 1904 (Folder 6)
- Lady Teazle articles, 1904-1906 (Folder 7)
- Wildfire - Articles and reviews, 1907-1909 (Folder 8)
- Green Book articles, 1909 (Folder 9)
- The Widow's Might - Articles and reviews, 1909 (Folder 10)
- Newspaper clippings, 1909-1910 (Folder 11)
- In Search of a Sinner - Articles and reviews, 1910 (Folder 12)
- Journal articles and newspaper clippings, 1911-1912 (Folder 13)
- Marriage to Alexander P. Moore and Weber & Fields Jubilee Company, 1912-1913 (Folder 14)
- Journal articles and newspaper clippings, 1913 (Folder 15)
- Journal articles and newspaper clippings, 1915 (Folder 16)
- Vaudeville tour, 1915-1916 (Folder 17)
- Journal articles, 1916 (Folder 18)
- Newspaper clippings, 1917-1918 (Folder 19)
- Immigration report - Journal articles and newspaper clippings, 1922 (Folder 20)
- Lillian Russell - Autobiographic articles in Cosmopolitan, 1922 (Folder 21)
- Death - Newspaper clippings, June 1922 (Folder 22-23)
- Funeral and remembrances - Journal articles and newspaper clippings, 1922 (Folder 24)
- Mary Reist/Alexander P. Moore correspondence, September 1923 (Folder 25)
- Alexander P. Moore will - Newspaper clippings (Folder 26)
- Lillian Russell beauty articles (Folder 27)
- Lillian Russell Room at Keith's Theatre - Philadelphia Record clipping, October 1924 (Folder 28)
- Dorothy Russell - My Mother, Lillian Russell articles in Liberty, 1929 (Folder 29)
- A.J. Liebling - Weber & Fields articles in the Pittsburgh Press, September 1932 (Folder 30)
- Helen Hayes - Just Living... article in Ladies Home Journal, April 1936 (Folder 31)
- Photographs and other images clipped from magazines (Folder 32)
- Journal articles and newspaper clippings, 1924-1951 (Folder 33)
- Chronology (Folder 34)